Meghna J.

Email: mxj3631@mavs.uta.edu

LinkedIn.com/in/meghna-j | GitHub.com/meghna-cse

Experience Summary: Software Engineer with 4+ years of software development experience, skilled in API integration, performance optimization, Java, Python, REST, and SOAP APIs. Demonstrated strong capabilities in team leadership, technological innovation, adopting new technologies, and teamwork within fast-paced environments.

EDUCATION

The University of Texas at Arlington

2022 to 2024

Master of Science in Computer Science

3.78/4.00 GPA

- Cloud Computing and Big Data, Web Data Management, Machine Learning, Data Mining, Secure Programming
- Graduate Teaching Assistant for Software Testing coursework in a software development life cycle.

Mukesh Patel School of Technology Management & Engineering, NMIMS University

2014 to 2018

Bachelor of Technology in Computer Engineering

First Class

- Distributed Computing, Object Oriented Software Engineering, Design & Analysis of Algorithms, Unix Programming

WORK EXPERIENCE

Software Developer, Student Assistant at The University of Texas at Arlington

2023 to 2023

- Led the transition and development of an IT portal to React and Node.js from the v1 PHP version, improving usability and security for end-users.
- Integrated SSO authentication, implemented role management, and refined the database, leading to improved access control and system efficiency.
- Collaborated with engineers to troubleshoot and resolve portal code issues for the v1 version, ensuring stability and robustness.

Software Engineer, Application Development at IBM India Private Limited (Gurgaon) Customer Integration Build Team

2018 to 2022

- Developed and maintained 25+ third-party integration applications using REST and SOAP APIs, including secure Apple Pay integration, to facilitate robust external banking communications and enhance system interoperability.
- Managed end-to-end feature development including backend debugging and root cause analysis, and led application deployment across environments via Jenkins pipeline, optimizing CI/CD processes.
- Led the migration of legacy applications to modern frameworks, implementing new coding standards and guidelines, significantly enhancing payment processing capabilities and boosting performance.
- Debugged and resolved critical production defects, improving customer record creation & modification workflows and application reliability through effective collaboration with the App Support team.
- Led a cloud migration team, training and mentoring new team members on modern tech stacks and coding standards, improving application scalability and team productivity.
- Built a Geolocation-based user authentication proof of concept using OpenStreetMap, Node.js, and IBM Cloud for Bank/ATMs. It made the team realize it's less costly to use third party messaging service.
- Implemented an Onboarding Application using Java, JavaScript, Spring, and MongoDB to track the progress of role-based activities and tasks for new hires in the Integration Build Team.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Programming: Java, Python, Groovy Scripting, JavaScript, React JS, HTML, CSS; REST and SOAP API development
- Framework/Tools: Spring Boot, Jenkins, SonarQube, SQL, IBM DB2, MySQL, IBM Message Queue, IBM Integration Bus (with ESQL and Java), IBM App Connect, IBM Cloud, Databricks, Git, Rational Team Concert (RTC)
- Testing: Unit Testing, System Testing, Junit, RFHUtil, SoapUl, ReadyAPI

PROJECTS

Beaver (LMS), github.com/meghna-cse/beaver

React | Node.js | Laravel | MySQL

Implemented UI and backend where key features were integrating role management and sentiment analysis for increased visitor engagement.

InputVal (REST API), github.com/meghna-cse/inputVal

Java | Spring Boot | Docker | API Development

Created a secure REST API for input validation, incorporating regular expressions, a phone book application with audit logs and secure data handling for enhanced security.

SOUL (Simulation of Objects in Unity for Learning), github.com/meghna-cse/SOUL

Unity3D | JS | HTML | CSS

Created an interactive web application simulating real-world scenarios to enhance learning in Physics.